Mss.Rec.84 Mss.Rec.84
American Philosophical Society
- Audio recordings
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 74-93, 1971-08; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:20:21; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 93-96, 1971-08; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:18; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. The subsequent entries from "body" (page 96) through "quiver" (page 98) are not on the tapes that comprise this collection. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 3.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 98-124, 1971-08; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 02:04:32; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. The prior entries from "body" (page 96) through through "quiver" (page 98) are not on the tapes that comprise this collection. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 3.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 124-149, 1971-08; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 01:54:31; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 1.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 150-173, 1971; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:48:56; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. Recording levels change slightly after 01:30:18. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 173-188, 1971; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:05:25; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    The first part of this program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. From 48:45 through the end of the recording, the program switches into a discussion of Hidatsa folklore, the history of Mandan and Hidatsa settlements in the area, nearby geographical locations, and miscellaneous aspects of Hidatsa material culture. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 2.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Dictionaries; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 188-192, 1971; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:35:20; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. From 18:15 - 30:29, discussion primarily concerns the meaning of the Hidatsa words for the Mandan people and the Hidatsa people respectively, the Crow people's words for themselves and the Hidatsa people, and the prevalence of the use of these languages and Mandan among each group. Approximately two pages of dictionary entries subsequent to those on this program are not on RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The researcher's voice is occasionally very faint at times during this program. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 2.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Mandan language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 194-195, 1971-08; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:10; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. Approximately two pages of dictionary entries prior to those on this program are not on RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 195-224, 1971; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 01:55:31; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 74, channel 3.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 225-255, 1971; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 02:00:30; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 1.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 255-283, 1971; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:23:36; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 1. When transferred to RDAT tape, the original recording spanned the end of one tape and the beginning of the subsequent one. As a result, there is a small gap in the recording at 02:01:11. Three seconds of silence were inserted to reflect the gap of missing original material, which is of underdetermined length, though likely no more than a few seconds.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 284-297, 1971; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:34:25; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. Approximately one page of dictionary entries subsequent to those on this program are not on RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 298-320, 1971; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 02:00:35; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. Approximately one page of dictionary entries prior to those on this program are not on RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 321-330, 1971; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:01:45; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 331-333, 1971; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:03; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program concludes a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 2.
  - Bull's Eye tradition of Lewis & Clark Bird Woman, 1971; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:29; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    In Hidatsa only. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 2.
    Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa language; Lewis and Clark Expedition (1804-1806); New Town (N.D.); Sacagawea
  - A First Creator story, 1971; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:43; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    Creation--Mythology; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa language; Hidatsa mythology; New Town (N.D.)
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 05-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:39; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    Begins with introductory remarks by researcher. This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 2.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:59:51; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 2.
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:39:45; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. There are intermittent stretches of increased background noise and poor tape quality from 01:16:34 to 01:23:00. Tape levels suddenly change at 01:26:58. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 2.
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:18:43; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 3.
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 06-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:54:32; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. The story in this program largely concerns Coyote. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 3.
    Anthropological linguistics; Coyote (Legendary character)--Legends; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Word analysis of Sacred Arrow Myth recorded with Sam Newman in Hidatsa, July 1932, 1971; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:34:23; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This recording consists of words and phrases elicited from a Hidatsa-speaking consultant. Some of the material is Hidatsa to English, some English to Hidatsa. The elicitations focus on prefixes and suffixes and are based on stories gathered by the researcher in 1939. Includes occasional discussions of details of Hidatsa social life and customs. The sound cuts out momentarily at 34:08, 49:54, and 01:23:47. Sound levels change at 01:23:50. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 75, channel 3.
  - Miscellaneous phrases translated into Hidatsa, 1971; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:44:24; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    In this program the researcher gives English sentences to the consultant, who then gives them back in Hidatsa. Interspersed throughout the program are occasional discussions of miscellaneous aspects of Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 76, channel 1.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Trip with Paul Ewald to family graves, 1971; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:05; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    In Hidatsa only.
    Anthropological linguistics; Cemeteries; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Data on tribal lands, 1971; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:58; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa language; Indian reservations--North Dakota; New Town (N.D.)
  - Traveling to Minot, 1971; 07-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:05; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    The account given by the speaker may in part concern the Influenza Epidemic of 1918-1919. Account given in Hidatsa only, with introductory comments in English.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; Influenza; Minot (N.D.); New Town (N.D.)
  - History of the Catholic Mission, 1971; 07-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:24; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    Account given primarily in Hidatsa, with some comments in English.
    Anthropological linguistics; Catholic Church--Missions--North Dakota; Hidatsa Indians--Education; Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Analysis of verb-adverb-adjective forms taken from Washington Matthews' Hidatsa Dictionary, 1971; 07-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:54; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James